Dr. Micheline Campbell

Postdoctoral Researcher, University College Dublin Brisbane, Australia (due to covid-19)
☐ +61 411 282 657
☑ michelineleecampbell@gmail.com
☑ michcampbell
☑ MichelineCampbell

Professional Summary

I have a PhD in speleothem palaeo-climatology and am currently employed as a postdoctoral researcher at University College Dublin, researching the palaeo-climate of eastern Australia, with a focus on water security. I have strong data and field science skills and have developed a research skillset applicable to a broad range of topics within the environmental sciences. My PhD research focused on stalagmite-based climate proxy records and associated karst geomorphology and groundwater hydrology, while my current position is focused on exploring future water security by expanding our knowledge of the palaeo-environment of eastern Australia. I am hoping to continue my career in physical geography by securing a position where I can apply skills I have developed in a meaningful way and contribute to the development of the next generation of geographers.

Education

- Aug 2014 PhD (Geography), School of Agriculture and Environment, The University Jul 2019 of Western Australia, Perth, Western Australia, Australia.
 - o Thesis: Speleothem-based palaeo-climate research: Methodology, applications, and insight from the Snowy Mountains, southeast Australia
 - o Supervisors: JN. Callow, H. McGowan, G.McGrath, H. Wong
 - Jul 2013 BA (Hons, 1st Class) (Geography), School of Geography, Planning, and
 Jun 2014 Environmental Management, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, QLD,
 Australia.
 - o Thesis: The Drip Hydrology of a Speleothem from the Yarrangobilly Caves, NSW, Australia
 - o Supervisors: H. Mcgowan, JN. Callow

Feb 2010 - **BA (Geography and Spanish)**, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Dec 2012 QLD, Australia.

Experience

Research

- Jul 2020 **Postdoctoral Researcher**, School of Geography, University College Dublin, present Dublin/Brisbane, QLD, Ireland/Australia.
 - o Contributing to the project 'Using Palaeo-climate Proxies for Water Security Planning'
 - o Undertook the majority of data science tasks for the development of a new database of Australian climate proxy data
- Feb 2020 **Scientist**, Land and Water Science Unit, QLD Dept. of Natural Resources, Jul 2020 Mining and Energy, Rockhampton, QLD, Australia.
 - o Analysed sugar cane trash trial data in relation to nutrient and sediment transport.
 - o Found that a significant proportion of the variation of sediment transported in cane paddock runoff can be described by soil type and cane trash cover.
 - o This was a short term 5-month contract
- Aug 2019 **Research Assistant**, School of Agriculture and Environment, University of Dec 2019 Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.
 - o Miscellaneous data analysis tasks
- Aug 2014 **PhD Researcher**, School of Agriculture and Environment, University of Jul 2019 Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.
 - o Developed two new palaeo-climate proxy records for south east Australia
 - Showed that the climate of the LIG had similar significant periodicities to present, suggesting our long term climate patterns (e.g. PDO) will continue as temperatures increase with climate change.
 - Used social network analysis to advance our understanding of methodologies applied in the speleothem palaeo-climate proxy community and the development of the field over time.
 - o Demonstrated that LA-ICP-MS and LA-ICP-AES of trace elements in speleothem calcite produce comparable results

Teaching

- 2018 **Tutor:** Geographies of a Global City, School of Agriculture and Environment, The University of Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.
- 2018 Course Co-Coordinator and Lecturer: Catchment and River Processes, School of Agriculture and Environment, The University of Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.
- 2014–2018 Tutor: Catchment and River Processes, School of Agriculture and Enviroment, The University of Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.

Teaching contributions include the delivery and creation of content for undergraduate and masters level units, both in the classroom/laboratory and in the field. Catchment and River Processes, which I taught into since its inception at UWA, consistently achieved high student ratings, including in 2018 when it received a score of 3.7/4. This placed it in the 70th percentile of UWA courses.

Funding and Scholarships

2018 Australian Institute of Nuclear Science and Engineering Travel grant.

o \$1000

- 2017 Australian and New Zealand Geomorphological Group Travel grant.
- 2016 University of Western Australia Travel grant.
 o \$1850
- 2015–2018 Australian Institute of Nuclear Science and Engineering Postgraduate Ressarch Award Stipend.

 o \$7500pa
- 2015–2018 Australian Institute of Nuclear Science and Engineering Postgraduate Ressarch Award Analytical Budget.

 o \$10000pa
- 2014–2018 Australian Government Research Training Program Stipend.

 o \$26000pa
- 2014–2015 Snowy Hydro Ltd. Stipend. $\circ $5000pa$
 - 2014 University of Western Australia Stipend.

 o \$3000

Publications

Published

- 1. McGowan, H., Campbell, M., Callow, J. N., Lowry, A., & Wong, H. (2020). Evidence of wet-dry cycles and mega-droughts in the Eemian climate of southeast Australia. *Scientific Reports*, 10(1), 1–10. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-75071-z
- 2. Campbell, M., Callow, J., McGrath, G., & McGowan, H. (2018). Co-authorship analysis of the speleothem proxy-climate community: working together to tackle the big problems. *International Journal of Speleology*, 47(2), 165–172. https://doi.org/10.5038/1827-806X. 47.2.2159
- 3. McGowan, H., Callow, J. N., Soderholm, J., McGrath, G., Campbell, M., & Zhao, J.-x. (2018). Global warming in the context of 2000 years of Australian alpine temperature and snow cover. *Scientific Reports*, 8(1), 4394. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-22766-z
- 4. Campbell, M., Callow, J. N., McGrath, G., & McGowan, H. (2017). A multimethod approach to inform epikarst drip discharge modelling: Implications for palaeo-climate reconstruction. *Hydrological Processes*, 31 (26), 4734–4747. https://doi.org/10.1002/hyp.11392

In Review

1. Croke, J., Vitkovsky, J., Hughes, K., Campbell, M., Sahar, A.-M., Parnell, A., Cahill, N., & Dalla Pozza, R. (2020). A palaeoclimate proxy database for water security planning. *Scientific Data, In Review*.

In Preparation

- 1. Campbell, M., & Wong, H. (n.d.-). LA-ICP-AES to analyse trace elements in speleothems. na.
- 2. Campbell, M., Callow, J. N., McGowan, H., Wong, H., & McGrath, G. (n.d.-). Solar forcing of mid-latitude terrestrial hydroclimate over the past 6.5 ka. na.

Conference Presentations

Talks

Feb 2017 A geophysical approach to inform epikarst drip discharge modelling: Implications for palaeo-climate reconstruction, Australian and New Zealand Geomorphological Group 17th Biennial Conference, Greytown, New Zealand, Campbell, M., Callow, J.N., McGrath, G.S., McGowan, H.A.

Posters

- Apr 2018 Climate patterns in South-east Australia: the Last Interglacial vs. the last 2K, 20th EGU General Assembly, Vienna, Austria, Campbell, M., Callow, J.N., McGowan, H.A., McGrath, G.S., Wong, H.
- Feb 2017 First Insights of the Eemian Hydroclimate of the Snowy Mountains, Australia, Australian and New Zealand Geomorphological Group 17th Biennial Conference, Greytown, New Zealand, Campbell, M., Wong, H., McGrath, G.S., McGowan, H.A., Callow, J.N.
- Dec 2016 First Insights of the Eemian Hydroclimate of the Snowy Mountains, Australia, American Geophysical Union, Fall Meeting, San Francisco, USA, Campbell, M. Wong, H., McGrath, G.S., McGowan, H.A., Callow, J.N.

Skills

Statistical

Statistical Software.

o R (advanced)

Statistical Methods.

- o Time series analysis
- o Hypothesis testing
- o Social network analysis
- o Linear models
- o Generalised linear models
- o Numerical modelling

Field

Surveying.

- o Total station
- o Real time kinematic

Electrical Resistivity Tomography.

- o Deployment
- o Data processing and analysis

Environmental Data Loggers.

- o Onset HOBO
- o In-Situ Rugged Troll
- o Driptych Stalagmate

Environmental Sampling.

- o Isotopes in water
- o Nutrients in water
- o Soil profiling

Other

Software.

- o Python (fundamental awareness)
- o ArcGIS (novice)
- o Microsoft Suite (advanced)
- o LaTEX (novice)
- o Rmarkdown (intermediate)

Service

- Aug 2017 Participant, Science in Schools Program.
- Aug 2017 o Travelled to a regional town to share some love for science with primary school kids
- Feb 2015 Postgraduate representative to the School of Earth and Environment.
 - Jul 2017 o Led the organisation of 2 annual symposia for postgraduate students within the school.
 - o Reported student concerns to the School administration
 - o Support and troubleshooting for new students
- Jan 2016 Co-Convenor, SEE LearnR Workshop.

Mar 2016

- Oct 2014 Guest presenter, ENVT2221: Global Climate Change and Oct 2014 Biodiversity.
 - o Presented 'Palaeo-climate and Stalagmites' for 2nd-year Biology students at UWA

Professional Development

- 2020 Advanced R Workshop. The University of Queensland, Australia
- 2020 Intermediate R Workshop. The University of Queensland, Australia
- 2018 Weathering Climate Change: How have humans coped with climate change-and how will we continue to do so. The University of Western Australia, Australia
- 2018 Masterclass in Creating Opportunities and Developing your Research Skills. The University of Western Australia, Australia
- 2016 Synthesis II From dynamics of structure to function of complex networks. TU Dresden, Germany
- 2016 Water on Earth: origin, reservoirs, and its global cycle. The University of Western Australia, Australia
- 2016 Fundamentals of the analysis of networks. The University of Western Australia, Australia

2014 Writing and publishing in scientific journals. The University of Western Australia, Australia

Referees

Post- **Professor Jacky Croke**, School of Geography, University College Dublin, Doctorate jacky.croke@ucd.ie.
Supervisor

PhD **Dr. Nik Callow**, School of Agriculture and Environment, The University of Supervisor Western Australia, nik.callow@uwa.edu.au; +61 8 6488 1924.